A Finding Aid to the Esta Nesbitt Papers, circa 1942-1981, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Project and Exhibition Files, circa 1966-1981; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 5.2 Linear feet Box 4-8, 11, 13, OV 17-19, 21, FC 22-23
  - "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
    - Everyman as Anyman Reel 23, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Super 8mm (Item FC 50)
      Note on box: #24. Other side of box: Everyman Reel #24 Burnt zeroxes #c. Note on preservation box: Everyman #24 Burnt Zeroxes #c (23 of 24 reels) Digitized 2014/16949 5.10. Head leader: Everyman Burnt Apr 69 #24. Tail leader: Huemark 4-17-69 #5553 Nesbitt Asoc. LTD. - Tail 2 - Reel - 24 - Tail.
    - Everyman as Anyman Reel 24, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Super 8mm (Item FC 51)
      Note on box: Oct 14/69 Everyman last reel "God" for insertion into film Henry Hecht plays "God". On other side of box: 7 God'. Note on preservation box: Everyman last reel "God" for insertion into film Oct 14/69 (24 of 24 reels) Digitized 2014/16949 5.10.
  - "Everyman God", 1969; Archival Resource Key
    - Everyman God Duplicate A, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Super 8mm (Item FC 26)
      Note on film box: "God" Oct 14/69 "Everyman duplicate A Henry Hecht plays 'God". Note on preservation box: Everyman "God" Duplicate A Henry Hecht Plays "God" Oct 14/69. Digitized 2014/17149 5.11.
    - Everyman God Duplicate B, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Super 8mm (Item FC 27)
      Note on film box: "God" "Everyman" last reel duplicate B Henry Hecht play "god". Note on preservation box: Everyman last reel "God" Duplicate B Henry Hecht plays "God". Digitized 2014/17151 5.11
  - "Folding/Struck", Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Notes, 1970; Archival Resource Key; Transcribed from notebook cover: "Jan 31.70 / Film 'Folding:Struck'" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Oversized material housed in Box 11, Folder 9.
    - Photographic Material, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Light Times 499", Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Preliminary Soundtrack by Anibal Ambert, 1971; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Light Times 499, 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 22)
      Label: Xerox Show Can. (top): XEROX Film AMBERT. Can (bottom): R-2337. Leader (HEAD): XEROX Head pix pos B&W A-wind, Ambert 3648.
    - Light Times 499 Work Print, 1972; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 23)
      Label: "Xerox" spliced-edited film on xerography. Can (top): I took off projector Jan 72. Can (bottom): Jan 6 72. Tape: 74 D.P. #4 5.2A 6L. Leader (TAIL): Ambert 5424. Leader (HEAD): Xerox Pix Pos B&W A-Wind Ambert 5424
  - "Memorial Exhibition of Drawing and Illustrations by Esta Nesbitt" (1977), Contact Sheets, Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - New York: Hold It!, Press Release and Kit, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment" (1970), Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Black Box, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Contact Sheets, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Guestbook, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Journals, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key; "Black Boxes" / July 30 '70 "Black Boxes" / Dec 2/70 (Box 7, Folder 14-16)
    - Notes, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Paintings, Photographic Material, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Poems of War and Revolution, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Source Material and Drafts, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19-21)
    - Installation Documents, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Sea of Movement, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23-24)
  - Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key; Transcribed from journal cover: "SHADOW" & PATHWAYS" ETC. 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Oversized material housed in Box 13 and OV 19.
  - Shadow Paintings, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    - Contact Sheets of Installation, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Illustrated Journal, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key; "shadow ptgs - color swatches etc / 1966/1967" (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Illustrated Journal, 1973; Archival Resource Key; "shadows May 1973 - For Exhibition WestBdwy" (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Negatives of Artwork, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Notebook, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key; Transcribed from notebook cover: Aug 9-70 - / shadow ptg / Summer 1970 - / Xerox Xplore / April 17.1971 / Xerox Xplore plans - new ideas for 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Notes, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Photograph Album of Works in Progress and Installation, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Photographic Material of Works in Progress, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1967-circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material, circa 1967-circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Transparencies of Exhibit, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Unidentified film, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel Super 8 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified sound recording, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Walk Up -- Tape On, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Funding Application, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Microfilm Record of Documents, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Notes, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key; "Nov 15-69 / Take my place - (stand in for me -)" (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Notes on Street Works, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key; "Sound Mar 10.70 for experimental tape / STREET WORKS Mar 21/70" (Box 8, Folder 15-16)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
      Oversized material for Folder 17 housed in Box 11, Folder 10.
    - Project Statement, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Transcript of Conversation with David Levy, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Xerography, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
  - "Xerography - Extensions in Art" (1971-1972), Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - All the Lines are Nines, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Big Eyes, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Exhibit Diagrams, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Journal, 1971; Archival Resource Key; "XEROX EXHIBITION - Book I / Aug 12-71 - Oct 25.71" (Box 8, Folder 26-27)
    - Journal, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key; "XEROX EXHIBITION - Book II / Oct-25.71 - Feb 28 '72" (Box 8, Folder 28-30)
    - Notes, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Photograph Album of Exhibit, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Photographic Material, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Press Material, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 34)
      Oversized material housed in OV 19.
  - Oversized from "Folding/Struck", Notes, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 3.
  - Oversized from "Folding/Struck", Printed Material, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 5.
  - Oversized from "Light Times 499", Photographic Material, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from in Box 7, Folder 7.
  - Oversized from "1000 Empty 49.3 Grams: A participatory environment" (1970), Notes, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 17.
  - Oversized from Shadow Paintings, Photographs of Exhibit, circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 5.
  - Oversized from Walk Up -- Tape On, Photographic Material, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 17.
  - Oversized from Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 25.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On" Notebook, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 13.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Notebook regarding Soundtrack, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 15.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Photographic Material, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 3.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Source Material, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 17)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folders 13 and 14.
  - Oversized from "Everyman as Anyman, or Putting On, On, On, On, On", Source Material, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 18)
    Oversized material from Box 6, Folder 9.
  - Oversized form Shadow and Pathways, Illustrated Journal, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 19)
  - Oversized from "Xerography - Extensions in Art" (1971-1972), Press Material, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 19)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folder 34.
  - 28 Motion Picture Film Reels from Box 4, folders 41-42 and Box 5, folder 1-11, Archival Resource Key (Box 21)
- Printed Material, circa 1963-1977; 1942-circa 1944; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Box 9-10, OV 20
  Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs include group and individual exhibitions. They are arranged based on Nesbitt's involvement with the exhibition and the medium of Nesbitt's work.
  Additional printed material is found throughout the collection.
  Printed Material contains books, catalogs, clippings, exhibition announcements, posters, magazines, and press releases. Included are published listings, reviews, and images of Nesbitt's work and exhibitions, and some of the clippings on xerography feature Nesbitt. The rest of the material reflects Nesbitt's interests, dealing with Chinese and Japanese literature, color, communication, creation and duplication of images electronically, energy, film, hallucinogenic experiences, painting, street works, and xerography. In comparison to the rest of the collection, the material in this series has little to no annotations; however, the book and magazine on film are heavily annotated.
  - Books, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Readings in American Art Since 1900: A Documentary Survey, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - An Introduction to the American Underground Film, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Who Am I? (NĀN YĀR?) of Bhagavan Sri Ramana Maharshi, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Children Books, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Children Books, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Parsons School of Design, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Art, Communication, and Computers, 1968-circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Arts College, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Book Excerpts and Reviews, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Oversized material housed in OV 20.
    - Color, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Nesbitt's Exhibitions and Works, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Painting, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Entropy, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - World War II, circa 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Xerox and Xerography, circa 1966-circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Nesbitt's Exhibitions, 1967-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Other Artists, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
    - Nesbitt's Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Nesbitt's Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Nesbitt's Paintings, Drawings and Prints, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Nesbitt's Xerography, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Nesbitt's Xerography, 1976; 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Other Artists, 1942; 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Posters, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Magazines, Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
    - Art and Exhibition Listings, 1970; 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Film, Color, and Electronic Image Creation, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper of Visual Studies Workshop, 1973 May; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Press Releases, 1970-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Student Publication of Parsons School of Design, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Technical Publication titled Ultraviolet and Fluorescence Photography, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Television Script titled "Doctor Einstein Before Lunch", 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Oversized Clippings, Book Excerpts and Reviews, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 9.
  - Oversized Clippings, Nesbitt's Exhibitions and Works, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 12.
  - Oversized Clippings, World War II, circa 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 14.
  - Oversized Clippings, Xerox and Xerography, circa 1966-circa 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 15.
  - Oversized Exhibition Announcements, Nesbitt's Exhibitions, 1967-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 9, Folder 16.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 8.
  - Oversized Magazines; Film, Color, and Electronic Image Creation, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 10.
  - Oversized Newspaper of Visual Studies Workshop, 1973 May; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 20)
    Oversized material from Box 10, Folder 11.